Register of the United States President's Famine Emergency Committee Records, 1946-1947
Hoover Institution Archives
United States President's Famine Emergency Committee Records
1946-1947
XX177
Hoover Institution Archives
31 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 2 envelopes (13 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, notes, and clippings, relating to food conservation in the United States and to famine conditions throughout the world. Includes memoranda and diaries of Herbert Hoover, honorary chairman of the committee.
United States. President's Famine Emergency Committee.
Access
Boxes 1-33 closed. Microfilm use copy available. Reels 29-31 and Boxes 31-33 may not be used without written permission of the trustees of the Hoover Foundation.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (31 reels).
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, reports, notes, and clippings, relating to food conservation in the United States and to famine conditions throughout the world. Includes memoranda and diaries of Herbert Hoover, honorary chairman of the committee.
Historical Note
The Famine Emergency Committee was established on March 1, 1946, by President Harry S. Truman for the purpose of aiding the fight against world famine. Herbert Hoover was named Honorary Chairman and Chester Davis, a St. Louis banker, was named Chairman. Together with the Department of Agriculture, the Committee sponsored world-wide food missions that sent Herbert Hoover to the governments of all important nations to enlist and coordinate them in a world front against famine.
Thirty-eight countries and states were visited: Great Britain, France, Italy, the Vatican, Germany, Austria, Belgium, Holland, Switzerland, Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Finland, Yugoslavia, Czechoslovakia, Poland, Greece, Egypt, Iraq, India, Thailand, the Philippines, China, Korea, Japan, Hawaii, Canada, Mexico, Panama, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, Chile, Argentina, Uruguay, Brazil, Venezuela, and Cuba.
Besides Hoover, members of the mission included Hugh Gibson, Dennis A. Fitzgerald, Perrin C. Galpin, Frank E. Mason, Maurice Pate, John B. Masdon, Charles F. Delzell, Hugo Meier, and Captain Hallam Tuck (USN).
(from Herbert Hoover, An American Epic, Volume IV, pp. 113-127)
Famines.; Food conservation.; Food supply.; International relief.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Honorary Chairman's File, 1946-1947 (Box 1.-14.)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, diaries,speeches, writings, reports, statistical data, press releases and statements, clippings, and other material relating to Herbert Hoover's role as Honorary Chairman of the Famine Emergency Committee, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - B (Folder 2-3)
      - C (Folder 4-5)
      - D (Folder 6)
      - E (Folder 7)
      - F (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - G (Folder 2)
      - H (Folder 3-4)
      - I-J (Folder 5)
      - K (Folder 6)
      - L (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - M (Folder 2-3)
      - N-O (Folder 4)
      - P (Folder 5)
      - R (Folder 6)
      - S (Folder 7)
      - S (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - T (Folder 2)
      - V-W (Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 4-6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Anderson, Clinton P. (Folder 3)
    - Davis, Chester C. (Folder 4)
    - Fitzgerald, Dennis A. (Folder 5)
    - Galpin, Perrin (Folder 6)
    - Gibson, Hugh (Folder 7)
    - Klein, Julius (Folder 8)
    - Kleinwaechter, Ludwig (Folder 9)
    - La Guardia, Fiorello (Folder 10)
    - Lochner, Louis P. (Folder 11)
    - Luce, Clare Booth (Folder 12)
    - McCabe, Charles B. (Folder 13)
    - McMullin, Dare Stark (Folder 14)
    - Mason, Frank E. (Folder 15)
    - Miller, Bernice (Folder 16)
    - Pawley, William (Folder 17)
    - Renner, Karl (Folder 18)
    - Stedman, Afred D. (Folder 19)
    - Stolper, Gustav (Folder 20)
    - Thomas, Lowell (Folder 21)
    - Truman, Harry S. (Folder 22)
    - Vogl, Oscar (Folder 23)
    - Voorhees, Tracy (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Wacker, Hedwig (Folder 2)
    - Walsh, Edmund A. (Folder 3)
  - Diaries, References to (Folder 4)
  - Letters to Herbert Hoover
    - Attacking (Folder 5)
    - Supporting (Folder 6)
  - Speeches and writings
    - Undated drafts and notes (Folder 7)
    - "Food, Relief, Famine and the Economic Front in World War II," n.d. Printed copy (Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous articles, 1946-1947 (Folder 9)
    - Press release, 1946 February 8. Typescript (Folder 10)
    - "Hoover Mourns Cowles," statement, 1946 February 28. Typescript (Folder 11)
    - Press conference, 1946 March 1. Typescript (Folder 12)
    - Memorandum for Secretary Anderson and Mr. Chester Davis, 1946 March 5. Typescript (Folder 13)
    - Press conference, 1946 March 12. Typescript (Folder 14)
    - Address on world famine, 1946 March 14. Typescript (Folder 15)
    - Address on world famine, 1946 March 17. Typescript (Folder 16)
    - Statement, 1946 May 10. Typescript (Folder 17)
    - "Reporting on the Famine Emergency," press conference, White House, 1946 May 13. Typescript (Folder 18)
    - "World Famine Situation," speech, Chicago, 1946 May 17. Mimeograph copy. Includes Spanish translation (Folder 19)
    - Speech, Washington, D.C., 1946 May 20. Mimeograph Spanish translation (Folder 20)
    - Speech, Bogota, Colombia, 1946 May 31. Mimeograph English translation of press account (Folder 21)
    - Speech, Santiago, Chile, 1946 June 5. Mimeograph Spanish translation (Folder 22)
    - Remarks, Montevideo, Uruguay, 1946 June 11. Mimeograph Spanish translation (Folder 23)
    - Statement on the Latin American food situation, 1946 June 19. Typescript (Folder 24)
    - "To the National Association of Women Directors of the National Association of Broadcasters," 1946 June 19. Typescript (Folder 25)
    - Statement, 1946 August 12. Typescript (Folder 26)
    - Statement, Salt Lake City, 1946 August 12. Typescript (Folder 27)
    - Statement, 1946 November 5. Typescript (Folder 28)
    - Speech at N.I.C. Board, 1946 November 17. Typescript (Folder 29)
    - Report No. 1 - Germany, 1947
      - Printed copies, February (Folder 30)
      - Clippings on public reaction to, March-April (Folder 31)
      - Clippings on public reaction to, March-April (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Report No. 2 - Austria, 1947
      - Galley proofs, typescripts and printed copies, March (Folder 3)
      - Clippings on public reaction to, March-April (Folder 4)
    - Report No. 3 - Germany/Austria, March 1947
      - Drafts and galley proofs (Folder 5)
      - Printed copies (Folder 6)
      - Clippings on public reaction to (Folder 7)
      - Clippings on public reaction to (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Subject file
    - Dulles, John Foster (Folder 3)
    - Economic assistance - Germany (Folder 4-6)
    - Economic assistance - Germany (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Folder 2)
    - Food missions
      - General (Folder 3)
      - Countries file. Research material on countries visited by Herbert Hoover
        - Argentina (Folder 4-5)
        - Austria (Folder 6)
        - Brazil (Folder 7)
        - Chile (Folder 8)
        - China (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - Colombia (Folder 2)
        - Cuba (Folder 3)
        - Czechoslovakia (Folder 4)
        - Ecuador (Folder 5)
        - Egypt (Folder 6)
        - Finland (Folder 7)
        - France (Folder 8)
        - Germany
          - General (Folder 9-11)
          - Clippings (Folder 12)
          - Letters to Herbert Hoover from German citizens (Folder 13)
          - Letters to Herbert Hoover from German citizens (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
        - Great Britain (Folder 3)
        - Greece (Folder 4)
        - India (Folder 5)
        - Iraq (Folder 6)
        - Italy (Folder 7)
        - Japan (Folder 8)
        - Korea (Folder 9)
        - Mexico (Folder 10-11)
        - Panama (Folder 12)
        - Peru (Folder 13-14)
        - Peru (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Philippine Islands (Folder 2)
        - Poland (Folder 3)
        - Sweden (Folder 4)
        - Switzerland (Folder 5)
        - Thailand (Folder 6)
        - Uruguay (Folder 7)
        - Venezuela (Folder 8)
        - Yugoslavia (Folder 9)
      - Itineraries
        - General (Folder 10)
        - Asian trips (Folder 11)
        - European trips (Folder 12)
        - South American trips (Folder 13)
      - List of members (Folder 14)
    - Gibson, Hugh (Box 14)
      - Notes on the European mission, 1946 March 17- May 12 (Folder 1)
      - Notes on the South American mission, 1946 May 25 - June 19 (Folder 2)
    - Lend-lease operations (1941-1945) - Soviet Union (Folder 3)
    - Marshall, George C. (Folder 4)
    - United States - Foreign relations - Japan (1947 March) (Folder 5)
    - Miscellany (Folder 6)
- Office File, 1945-1947 (Box 14.-22.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, statistical data, clippings, and printed matter, relating to the daily operations of the Famine Emergency Committee, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Agreements between the U.S. and recipient governments (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Cable codes (Folder 8)
  - Clippings
    - General, 1946
      - February-March (Folder 9)
      - March (Folder 10)
      - April (Folder 11)
      - April (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
      - May (Folder 3-4)
      - June-September (Folder 5)
    - Hoover trip to Germany, 1947. In German (Folder 6)
    - Hoover trip to Germany, 1947. In German (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Office of Price Administration (Folder 3)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - American National Red Cross, 1946 (Folder 5)
  - Exhibits file (Folder 6)
  - Membership list (Folder 7)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1946 March-April (Folder 8)
  - Publicity file (Folder 9)
  - Subject file
    - Anti-Nazi League (Folder 10)
    - Child health and welfare. Reports on conditions in various countries by Maurice Pate, 1946 (Folder 11)
    - Displaced persons, immigrants, refugees, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Economic assistance, American
      - Greece and Turkey (Folder 2)
      - Turkey (Folder 3)
    - Economic Cooperation Administration (Folder 4)
    - Emergency Economic Committee for Europe (Folder 5-6)
    - Europe
      - Economic conditions, 1945-1947 (Folder 7)
      - History - 1945-1947 (Folder 8)
      - Industries (Folder 9)
    - European Recovery Program (Folder 10)
    - European Recovery Program (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
    - Food consumption
      - Far East (Folder 4)
      - Romania (Folder 5)
      - South Africa (Folder 6)
      - United States (Folder 7)
    - Food supply
      - General (Folder 8)
      - General (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
      - Europe (Folder 4)
      - Europe (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Food for Freedom, Inc. (Folder 2-3)
      - Grains (Folder 4-5)
      - Potatoes (Folder 6)
      - South America (Folder 7-8)
    - Germany - History - 1945-1955 (Box 21)
      - General (Folder 1-2)
      - U.S. Army food surplus, 1947 (Folder 3)
    - Health conditions
      - Europe (Folder 4)
      - Hungary (Folder 5)
    - National Famine Emergency Council. List of members, 1946 March 13 (Folder 6)
    - National Retail Committee (Folder 7)
    - Neutral zones in wartime (Folder 8)
    - Raw materials - Africa (Folder 9)
    - Refugees Defence Committee, London (Folder 10)
    - State Food Emergency Program (Folder 11)
    - Turkey - Economic conditions - 1946-1947 (Folder 12)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA)
      - General (Folder 13)
      - Economic Notes
        - 1946
          - January-September (Folder 14)
          - October-December (Folder 15)
        - 1947 January-February (Folder 16)
    - United States (Box 22)
      - Appropriations, 1947 (Folder 1)
      - Food exports, 1945-1946 (Folder 2)
      - Food saving proposals by the Girl Scouts of America and other organizations (Folder 3)
      - Foreign trade (Folder 4)
      - Legislation for relief assistance (Folder 5)
    - United States. Maritime Commission (Folder 6)
    - United States Information Service. Newsletter issues and press releases, 1946 (in Portuguese) (Folder 7)
    - World War, 1939-1945 - Aerial operations, American (Folder 8)
- Countries File, 1946-1947 (Box 22.-28.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statistical data, surveys, and printed matter, relating to the countries visited by Herbert Hoover and the Famine Emergency Committee team, arranged alphabetically by name of country
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, statistical data, surveys, and printed matter
  - Argentina (Box 22)
    - Description (Folder 9)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 10)
    - Relief to other countries (Folder 11)
  - Austria
    - General (Folder 12)
    - Food consumption (Folder 13)
    - Food supply (Folder 14)
    - Health and welfare
      - General (Folder 15)
      - Children (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Brazil
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 3)
    - Hoover trip to, 1946 June (Folder 4-5)
  - Chile (Folder 6)
  - China
    - Appeal for aid to the U.S. (Folder 7)
    - Food supply (Folder 8)
  - Colombia
    - Food supply (Folder 9)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 10)
  - Cuba
    - Food supply (Folder 11)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 12)
  - Czechoslovakia (Folder 13)
  - Ecuador
    - Food supply (Folder 14)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 15)
  - Egypt (Folder 16)
  - Finland (Folder 17)
  - France
    - General (Folder 18)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 19-20)
    - Nutrition (Folder 21)
  - Germany
    - General (Folder 22)
    - Agriculture (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Child feeding programs (Folder 2)
    - Concentration camps (Folder 3)
    - Denazification (Folder 4)
    - Economic conditions, 1946-1947 (Folder 5)
    - Fisheries (Folder 6)
    - Food consumption (Folder 7)
    - Food supply (Folder 8-10)
    - Foreign relations - Soviet Union (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Foreign trade (Folder 2)
    - Forestry (Folder 3)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 4-7)
    - History - 1945-1955
      - British occupied zone (Folder 8)
      - Postwar unification (Folder 9)
      - Reconstruction (Folder 10)
    - Industry (Box 26)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Industrial disarmament (Folder 2)
    - Land reform (Folder 3)
    - Nutrition
      - General (Folder 4-6)
      - Berlin (Folder 7)
      - Cologne and North Rhine region (Folder 8)
      - Hamburg (Folder 9)
    - Politics and government (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Relief organizations
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Council of Relief Agencies Licensed for Operation in Germany (Folder 3)
    - Shipping (Folder 4)
    - Social conditions (Folder 5)
  - Great Britain
    - Food supply (Folder 6)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 7)
  - Greece - Economic assistance, American (Folder 8)
  - India (Folder 9)
  - Italy
    - General (Folder 10)
    - Economic assistance, American (Folder 11)
    - Food supply (Folder 12)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 13)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) (Folder 14)
    - United States. Embassy (Italy). Office of the Press Attache - U.S. correspondents in Italy, 1947 February (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Japan
    - Fertilizers (Folder 2)
    - Food supply (Folder 3-4)
    - Natural resources (Folder 5)
    - Nutrition (Folder 6)
  - Mexico
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Food supply (Folder 8)
  - Netherlands
    - General (Folder 9)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 10)
  - Norway - Fish exports (Folder 11)
  - Panama (Folder 12)
  - Peru
    - Food supply (Folder 13)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 14)
  - Poland
    - Economic assistance, American (Folder 15)
    - Food supply (Folder 16)
  - Sweden
    - Food consumption (Folder 17)
    - Food supply (Folder 18)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 19)
    - Relief to other countries (Folder 20)
  - Switzerland (Folder 21)
  - Thailand (Folder 22)
  - Uruguay
    - Food supply (Folder 23)
    - Health and welfare (Folder 24)
- Card Index File, n.d. (Box 29.-30.)
  Card index file of individual and organizational donors to the Famine Emergency Committee, arranged alphabetically by donor
  - Card index file of individual and organizational donors to the Famine Emergency Committee. Arranged alphabetically by donor (Box 29-30.)
  - Yugoslavia (Folder 25)
- Honorary Chairman's File, 1945-1947 (Restricted Section) (Box 31.-33.)
  Correspondence, diaries, speeches, writings, reports, statistical data, press releases and statements, clippings and other material relating to Herbert Hoover's role as Honorary Chairman of the Famine Emergency Committee, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence
    - Buck, Pearl (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - La Guardia, Fiorello (Folder 2)
    - Mason, Frank E. Includes letters to Julius Klein (Folder 3)
    - Meier, Hugo. Includes Hugo Meier's diary (Folder 4)
    - Pate, Maurice (Folder 5)
    - Ready, Frank (Folder 6)
  - Diary
    - 1946
      - March 21-25. France (Folder 7)
      - March 22-24. Italy (Folder 8)
      - March 25. Switzerland (Folder 9)
      - March 28. Czechoslovakia (Folder 10)
      - March 28-30. Poland (Folder 11)
      - March 31 - April 1. Finland (Folder 12)
      - April 1-2. Sweden (Folder 13)
      - April 2-3. Norway (Folder 14)
      - April 4-6. Great Britain (Folder 15)
      - April 6-8. Belgium (Folder 16)
      - April 9. Netherlands (Folder 17)
      - April 10. Denmark (Folder 18)
      - April 11-13. Germany (Folder 19)
      - April 14-15. Austria (Folder 20)
      - April 16. Yugoslavia (Folder 21)
      - April 16-18. Greece (Folder 22)
      - April 18-20. Egypt (Folder 23)
      - April 21-22. Iraq (Folder 24)
      - April 22-26. India (Folder 25)
      - April 27. Thailand (Folder 26)
      - April 28-29. Philippine Islands (Folder 27)
      - April 30 - May 3. China (Folder 28)
      - May 4. Korea (Folder 29)
      - May 4-6. Japan. Includes interview with General Douglas MacArthur (Folder 30)
      - May 7-8. Hawaii (Folder 31)
      - May 25 - June 20. South America (Folder 32)
    - 1947
      - Various dates (Folder 33)
      - February. Germany (Folder 34)
  - Founding documents (Folder 35)
  - Minutes of meetings with Harry S. Truman, Clinton Anderson, Robert Patterson and others, 1946 March 1-12 (Folder 36)
  - Speeches and writings (Box 32)
    - Untitled drafts and notes
      - Argentina (Folder 1)
      - Brazil (Folder 2)
      - Columbia (Folder 3)
      - Displaced persons (Folder 4)
      - Ecuador (Folder 5)
      - Food
        - Statistics (Folder 6)
        - Surplus (Folder 7)
      - Germany (Folder 8)
      - Greece (Folder 9)
      - Latin America (Folder 10)
      - Mexico (Folder 11)
      - Peru (Folder 12)
      - Poland (Folder 13)
      - Russia (Folder 14)
      - Sweden (Folder 15)
      - Thailand (Folder 16)
      - Yugoslavia (Folder 17)
      - Miscellany (Folder 18)
    - "Germany - Mistakes at Potsdam," n.d. Typescript (Folder 19)
    - Memorandum to Chester Davis regarding the broadcasting of Herbert Hoover's final report from Canada, n.d. Holograph (Folder 20)
    - Press conferences and press releases, 1946 March. Drafts, notes, and typescripts (Folder 21)
    - "World Famine Situation," speech, Chicago, 1946 May 17. Handwritten and typewritten drafts (Folder 22)
    - Address in Mexico City, 1946 May 28. Holograph and typescript (Folder 23)
    - Report to President Truman, 1946 June 9. Handwritten and typewritten drafts (Folder 24)
    - Statement on the Latin American food situation, Washington, D.C., 1947 June 19. Typescript (Folder 25)
    - Final report broadcast from Canada, Ottawa, 1946 June 28. Typewritten and printed draft (Folder 26)
    - "Crimes in Food," 1946 September 13. Holograph and typescripts (Folder 27)
    - Economic report to the President, 1947. Handwritten and typewritten drafts (Folder 28)
  - Subject file
    - Brazil - Food statistics, 1945 (Folder 29)
    - Food missions
      - Countries visited
        - Austria (Folder 30)
        - Brazil (Folder 31)
      - European trip (Box 33)
        - 1946 March 17 - May 12 (Folder 1)
        - 1947 February (Folder 2)
      - Pate, Maurice, "Some Notes on the Trip with the Hoover Mission, May-June 1946" (Folder 3)
      - South American trip, 1946
        - Account by Hugh Gibson of Herbert Hoover's trip (Folder 4)
        - Correspondence. Includes letters of appreciation (Folder 5)
        - Immunization record of Herbert Hoover (Folder 6)
        - Itinerary (Folder 7)
        - Lists of crew members and participants (Folder 8)
        - Telegrams
          - General (Folder 9)
          - Miller, Bernice (Folder 10)
    - Venereal disease incidence among U.S. troops in Europe (Folder 11)
    - World food conditions (Folder 12)
- Photographs, 1946-1947
  137 prints depicting Herbert Hoover and and other members of the Famine Emergency Committee European and Asian food mission
  - 117 prints depicting Herbert Hoover and other members of the Famine Emergency Committee on the European and Asian food missions (Box 1)
  - 20 United Press International prints depicting officials and operations of the U.S. President's Famine Emergency Committee (Box 2)